Handling errors locally in components makes sense a lot because you probably want to do different things
Bileenlerin iindeki hatalarn yerel olarak ele alnmas mantkldr nk muhtemelen hangi bileen olduunuza
with errors depending on in which component you're at.
bal olarak hatalarla farkl eyler yapmak istemektedir.
Maybe here you want to show something went wrong and in another component, you want to show something
Belki burada bir eylerin yanl gittiini ve farkl bir ey gstermek istediiniz ayrlmaz bir bileen olduunu
different
gstermek istersiniz.
but sometimes in some places, you maybe want to execute some code globally.
Ancak bazen baz yerlerde baz kodlar genel olarak yrtmek isteyebilirsiniz.
So no matter which HTTP request you send, from within which component, you want to do something when that
Bu nedenle hangi bileen iinde gnderdiiniz HTP istei ne olursa olsun, bu istek gnderildiinde
request gets sent and or when the response returns.
veya yant geldiinde bir eyler yapmak istiyorsunuz.
You can do it with axios with the help of so-called interceptors,
Szde ilgi alan belirleyicilerinin yardmyla X yana kadar bunu yapabilirsiniz.
these are functions you can define globally which will be executed for every request leaving your app
Bunlar, genel olarak tanmlayabileceiniz, uygulamanzdan ayrlan ve her yant iine geri gnderen her
and every response returning into it.
istek iin idare edilecek ilevlerdir.
This is especially useful for example for setting some common headers like authorization header maybe
rnein, teklif ba veya belki de yantlar gibi baz ortak balklarn ayarlanmas
or for responses
iin zellikle yararldr.
if you want to log responses or want to handle errors globally. I will show you how to add interceptors
Yantlar gnle kaydetmek isterseniz veya hatalar genel olarak ele almak iin 1 bu resmedilmede nasl
in this lecture.
nlem alacanz gstereceim.
Let's go to the index.js file because this is the most global file we have in our react app,
Bir dahaki dosyaya geelim, nk bu bir saatlik yeniden eyleme gememiz gereken en genel dosya.
it's the file where we actually start our react app by mounting it to the dom.
afa takarak tepkimemize baladmz derin bir dosya.
So here, I now also want to import axios from the axios package and all these axios imports actually
te imdi x yln Xs paketinden almak istiyorum ve tm bu X yllk
all share the same configuration.
ithalat aslnda ayn yaplandrmay paylayor.
So that is why we cannot also use axios here and axios is a special interceptor's object,
Dolaysyla, buradaki eriimi de kullanamayacamz iin X bir zel ilgi alan belirleyicisinin nesnesi.
and again, this will be then shared not only in this file but across all files in your project
Ve tekrar bu yalnzca bu dosyada deil, projenizdeki tm dosyalar arasnda paylalacaktr.
so it will affect all requests sent from anywhere in your app.
Bu, uygulamanzn herhangi bir yerinde sylenen tm istekleri etkileyecektir.
There we can access the request object and now I'll simply add use to register a new interceptor, that
Orada, istek nesnesine eriebilir ve imdi, Sadr'n akmay ya da syleyebildiiniz istei alan
interceptor takes a function as an input which receives the config or the request you could say.
bir girdi olarak ilgisini ekecek yeni bir mdahale kaydettirmek iin kullanm ekleyebilirsiniz.
Now let's simply log that request to the console for now so that we can see what's inside of it.
imdilik iptal edilmek zere bu talebi sadece kilitleyelim, bylece iinde bulunanlar grebiliyoruz.
I'm calling it request but it mainly is just to request config, that's important to keep in mind.
steim aryorum, ancak esas olarak yalnzca aklda tutulmas gereken atma talebinde bulunmaktr.
Now let's save this
imdi bunu kurtaralm.
and if we go back to the app, we immediately see something in the log.
Ve uygulamaya geri dnersek, gnlkte bir eyler grebiliriz.
This is the request which was sent, the request configuration at least. You see the headers which are added
ISDE istei hangi istek yaplandrmas gnderildi istiyor mu en azndan eklenen balklar gryorsunuz
and
ve.
yes
Evet.
this is our request,
Bu bizim isteimiz.
this is what we got sent here when we got the posts.
Buraya mesaj geldiinde buraya gnderdik.
Now something went wrong here though because we actually are blocking the requests right now.
imdi burada bir ey ters gitti, nk aslnda u anda isteklerini engelliyorduk.
In your interceptor function here, you need to always return the request or the request config
Faiz setter ilevinizde, her zaman istei veya istei iade etmeniz gerekir.
otherwise you're blocking the request.
Aksi takdirde istei engelliyorsunuz.
Now of course you can also edit the request config before you return it,
Artk, istei atmay, iade etmeden nce de deitirebilirsiniz.
that's the idea behind the interceptor,
Engelleyicinin arkasndaki fikir budur.
you can add headers, do stuff like that.
Balklar, byle eyler yaparak ekleyebilirsiniz.
So now if we save this, we get the posts and if I click on one, you will see another log because another
imdi bunu kaydedersek mesajlarmz alrz ve birisine tklarsam, numara istei gnderildi ve drt kii ld,
request was sent and for that,
nk bir numara kilidi greceksin.
the interceptor also ran even though it was fired from a different component,
Engelleyici de farkl bir bileenden atlm olmasna ramen kotu.
as I said all components, all areas of your app are covered with that.
Dediim gibi, tm bileenlerin Avrupa'daki tm paralar bu kapsamda.
Now for that interceptor here,
imdi burada l mdahale iin.
we can also pass a second function besides that request configuration changing function,
stee bal yaplandrma deitirme ilevinin yan sra ikinci bir ileve geebiliriz.
we can add a function which handles any errors.
Hatalar ileyen bir fonksiyon ekleyebiliriz.
So here we can log an error like this,
Yani burada byle bir hatay kaydedebiliriz.
we should also return promise reject error here though so that we still forward it to our request as
gstermek iin yapmak istediin baz yerel grevin varsa akla mantkl geliyor. UI'da bir ey var ama ayn zamanda
we wrote it in a component where we can handle it again with the catch method, this make sense if you
genel olarak bir sunucuya veya benzer bir eye gnderdiiniz gnlk dosyasna girmek istiyorsunuz.
have some local task you want to do like show something on the UI but also globally, you want to log
Ayrca burada sz reddetme hatamz geri evirmeliyiz, bylece talebi reddettiimiz halde talebimize ynlendiriyoruz, bylece onu catch
it in the log file which you send to a server or something like that.
yntemi ile tekrar ele alabileceimiz bir paraya yazdm,
So let's see how this works
Bu yzden nasl altn grelim.
if I now save that file and now turn my posts, my get posts URL invalid again.
Dosyay imdi kaydettiysem ve mesajlarm evirirsem mesajlarm alrsam yine geersiz saylrsn.
Now you see something went wrong here but you don't actually see the console log from the error handler,
imdi burada bir eylerin ters gittiini gryorsunuz, ancak aslnda maliyeti ok fazla grmyorsanz, hata
from the interceptor.
ileyicisinin engelleyiciden geldiini gryoruz.
The reason for this is that this error here is related to sending the request,
Bunun sebebi, bu havalandrcnn talebin gnderilmesiyle ilgilidir.
for example if you had no internet connectivity or something like that, it should pop up
rnein, nternet balantnz yoksa byle bir ey alr.
so if the request sending fails. We can also add an interceptor to handle responses though, we do in the
Fales gndermeyi talep ederseniz, yant isteini ilemek iin bir arabir ekleyebiliriz, ancak istek
same way as you do it for the request but we use the response object on the interceptors object.
iin yaptnz gibi yaptmz halde, yant nesnesini interceptors nesnesinde kullanrz.
Then we also use two functions here, one function and I'm copying it from above,
O zaman iki ilevi burada bir ilev kullanyoruz ve yukardan kopyalyorum.
one function which will receive the success response, we can also log it here and we should return it
Baar tepkisini alacak bir ilevi burada da kaydedebiliriz ve geri getirmeliyiz,
so that we can also still use it in the component in the then block.
bylece hepimizi daha sonra bloktaki bileende kullanabiliriz.
So that is one way we should return it and we also fetch errors and we should also reject them here
Bu bir ekilde geri vermeliyiz ve hepimiz hatalar buluyoruz ve bunlar tekrar burada tekrar kontrol
so that we can still handle them in the catch block locally in a component.
etmeliyiz ki bylece bunlar yine de catch blounda bir bileende yerel olarak ileyebiliriz.
Now with that added, with that response interceptor added and the error function being present, now if we go
Baba bu yant ekledi ve ekledi ve ekledi ve imdi hata fonksiyonu mevcut geri gidiyoruz.
back,
imdi eer
we actually see the log here and we still handle it locally,
Aslnda buray gryoruz ve hala yerel olarak idare ediyoruz.
so both works.
Yani ikisi de ie yarar.
If I now go to the block container and turn my
imdi blok konteynerine gidip benimkini geri getirirsem.
URL into a valid URL again,
Geerli olduunuza gre yeniden hastalsnz.
we see just the log for the response.
Yant iin sadece bir kilit gryoruz.
So this is coming from the interceptor as you can tell by the file name and line number
Dosya ad ve satr numarasyla syleyebildiiniz gibi bu, durdurucudan geliyor.
and this is another way of course of potentially manipulating that response here or logging it or doing
yant potansiyel olarak burada maniple etmek ya da gnle kaydetmek ya da istediiniz her eyi yapmann baka bir yoludur.
whatever you want.
Ve bu, bu
So being able to define these interceptors can be quite powerful,
Dolaysyla Deis ncllerini tanmlayabilmek olduka gl olabilir.
again a very common use case is for the request interceptor to add some common headers
Yine ok yaygn kullanlan bir durum, istek engelleyicisinin ortak baz stbilgiler eklemesidir.
for example, an authorization header. Though we also have a different way of accessing global axios configuration,
rnein, bir yetkilendirme bal olsa da, kresel eriim yaplandrmasna farkl bir ekilde erime imknmz da mevcuttur.
I'll show you how this works in the next lecture.
Bunun bir sonraki resimde nasl altn gstereceim.